[Applause]
the end of the berin wall is a symbol of
the end of a divided Europe and the end
of C War nobody could believe this was
real it was a
miracle for the they were at the door
shiting the wall is open we walk through
the wall the day the war came down will
be the most joyful days of my life I've
never seen so many plainly happy people
and faces in my life again so where
people were just not even smiling there
were just this joy and
disbelief nobody could foresee how and
if and when it would happen I mean it
was brought down
by the Soviet Reform movement developing
which then spread to Eastern Europe and
then the strength of people in these
various countries particularly in East
Germany and beginning to demonstrate
gorbachov came to East Germany to
celebrate uh the country's 40th
anniversary of its foundation as a
communist state and people lined the
streets and and shouted gorby gorby help
us Gorbachev is not the head of a third
class Banana Republic but he is happens
to be the head of the number one
socialist country and if he talks about
the
necessity of opening
up and uh realistically portraying and
presenting problems in our own countries
then uh not everything is lost then
there's Reason for
Hope there was so much happening there
was a stazzi headquarters being stormed
you had to dash there was a press
conference by one of the Democracy
movements you had to dash so you you
heard these things you saw them on an
East German television or ADN there was
no there were no mo mobile phones you
weren't told anything you have to find
out yourself what was happening by going
to the Press Center and you were
constantly on the road and you know
chasing one story after the other and so
it was in the 9th of November on the
evening of that day G chabowski gave his
press conference during which he was
handed this piece of paper saying that
East Germany would open its borders to
the west and he read it out almost as if
it was an accident of history and
afterthought that East Germany was
opening its borders
party leadership actually didn't intend
the wall to come down they made a
mistake they announced a decision which
was meant to be saying at you know in
the next few hours we're going to make
it possible for people to cross the
board without visas they said it's
happening now and people rushed
out at 11:30 p.m. one of the uh
commanding officers just decided to open
the gate uh because there were too many
people he could couldn't hold back
anymore people were streaming to the
wall in the Eastern side and coming on
the other side from the west and they
didn't immediately Rush one or two
tested what the folks Poli ey would do
and the Border guards whether they would
shoot because nobody believed this was
for
[Music]
real but eventually one or two went
across and then just screams and screams
followed and one trabant after the other
Road
it's wonderful we are we have seen it in
TV it it was
super then half my daughter's class
arrived at our door in the middle of the
night really excited shouting the wall
is open we walk through the wall I knew
them all they came up to our flat and I
got all the alcohol out of the fridge
and we celebrated our
reunion my neighbor came and rang the
the door and said Eliz aeth
often so grab your ID card and come the
wall is everybody goes everybody's
leaving we went to Checkpoint Charlie
because this is where what was open and
we didn't have the right money at that
time in the middle of the night and
there was everybody there so a huge
party without alcohol because nobody had
anything in the morning Big East German
mechanical diggers came and made a hole
in the wall near the Brandenburg gate
because there was a big rally with vly
brunt and hwood Cole a big historic
rally as big and historic and important
as Kennedy's visit to to Berlin so many
years
before a lot of uh people came with
little chisels and Hammers and pecked
away at the wall to take little bits
away because it it it was surely going
to be a very important uh
memorabilia to have in the future I was
totally under some sort of cultural
shock I couldn't stand all the choice
and all the uh sort of these colorful
things each time I came back from R
Berlin I was sort of I rested my eyes I
literally rested my eyes and my soul and
was happy to be back in the East my gray
East just because the all these colors
were way too much for us
the aims of the people were
demonstrating initially and I think the
expectation of most people who were
analyzing it and Reporting on it and
watching it was that this would reform
the system that the system would have to
reform they didn't think that the war
would come down and the Germany would be
reunited somehow it was thought that
that wasn't going to happen